Jenna Monroy: I am! Is everybody ready to go?
Jenna Monroy: Do you guys all have your World Cup brackets filled out?
Jenna Monroy: No? Is everybody watching? I mean, is there a game on right now?
Jenna Monroy: The things we do for science, we can't actually watch are soccer games. It's, it's all good. It's all good. We'll, we'll catch up on the highlights later.
Jenna Monroy: Welcome, everybody! I'm really excited to be here. For those of you who don't know me, I'm Jenna Monroy. I'm at the Claremont Colleges, and so I am in sunny California, but I know many of you are tuning in from other places, so it's morning for me, it might be afternoon for all of you. I'm gonna go ahead and share my screen, but keep in mind that what I'm gonna end… I'm gonna end up sharing a screen and then unsharing, and things like that.
Jenna Monroy: Hopefully I'm sharing the right thing. Okay.
Jenna Monroy: So… Me.
Jenna Monroy: Let me first, hold on.
Jenna Monroy: Good.
Jenna Monroy: All right, can everybody see the right screen? It should be a big screen that just says, welcome to the IMSI Summer Workshop number one. Let me just go back first. So does… has everybody signed in?
Jenna Monroy: And, so that, you know, you get… sign into the workshop and the reflection. I'm just gonna put that up there for right now. You can scan it, make sure everybody's in.
Jenna Monroy: Where they need to be.
Victoria Wood: We actually have your presenter mode right now, just as a…
Jenna Monroy: Wrong one! Hold on, let me… let me see if I can do this again. Okay, so let's stop sharing. You can tell I'm not really a Zoom person. In fact, I really hate Zoom, just… just so you guys all know that. Okay, I'm gonna try this again, so we'll do…
Jenna Monroy: that one. And then, if I go here…
Jenna Monroy: Do you see the right screen this time?
Victoria Wood: Yes.
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Jenna Monroy: Lovely.
Jenna Monroy: Anyway, again, I'm Jenna Monroe, and like all of you, I'm interested in how animals move and how muscles function, and I was thinking about, you know, what to do for the first workshop of the summer, and I thought it would be best that we actually review the basic principles of muscle function before you guys dive into your research and learn about all these other
Jenna Monroy: Research projects that everyone else is doing.
Jenna Monroy: And so…
Jenna Monroy: we are at different stages of our career. Some of you know a lot about muscle, and some of you, this is your first time really thinking about muscle. So, what I encourage you guys to do today is, for those of you that are further along in your career, you know, I encourage you to act as a mentor today. You might know more than someone else, and so get them up to the same level as you, so that we can think about
Jenna Monroy: muscle together. The other thing to know is that we cannot cover everything there is to know about muscle in a single workshop, and so the goal of today is really review those general principles of muscle physiology. I'm also going to encourage ourselves and others
Jenna Monroy: To think across biological scales, and hopefully we can generate some discussion about aspects of muscle function that are not well understood.
Jenna Monroy: Okay, so, you know.
Jenna Monroy: like you guys, I'm interested in studying movement, and one of the remarkable things about the muscular system is that it's so highly conserved across animals. The way that they are organized, how force is generated, and even how they respond to length and activation.
Jenna Monroy: And so, this allows us to identify these sort of fundamental principles and common mechanisms, and it allows us to make broad claims about how muscles function across species.
Jenna Monroy: And this is why we can study so many different organisms. I was struck by all the diversity of projects that you all are taking part in.
Jenna Monroy: This summer, I saw locomotion and tree shrews and k-rats, you know, studying bullfrogs, guinea fowls, and I even saw a project on balance in pregnant women. And it sounds so exciting to learn about how muscles are functioning in all these different organisms.
Jenna Monroy: Now, we can also take the alternative approach, right, is that we have to recognize that muscles are versatile and adaptive. They can function in so many different ways, not only as motors, but also as springs, or brakes, or struts, and
Jenna Monroy: Their properties are finely tuned to meet the demands of a particular behavior, and we have to think about those small, subtle differences, in muscle, maybe in its structure, or maybe a protein isom form.
Jenna Monroy: Or it's architecture or neural control that can alter and potentially even dramatically alter,
Jenna Monroy: an animal's performance. And so we really need to consider both perspectives. We need to think about this generalized muscle perspective, or this specialized muscle perspective, to help us understand how a common biological system can lead to such remarkable functional diversity. Okay.
Jenna Monroy: So our goal today is to…
Jenna Monroy: Essentially, we want to be able to learn… explain the fundamental principles of muscle physiology. Think about what you learn in your physiology class, right? And we'll talk a lot about what did we learn in physiology, and what are we learning here.
Jenna Monroy: I also am going to emphasize that we think about variation across muscles and species, so where are those subtle changes taking place?
Jenna Monroy: We're going to evaluate muscle function across biological levels of organization. Many of us work at one level. Maybe we study animal performance, and we don't often think about those molecular mechanisms that are taking place. Alternatively, there's people who study myofibrils, and they never really think about the animal performance. We're going to try to emphasize that all of us work across those scales.
Jenna Monroy: And lastly, I'm going to have us try to identify limitations of current theories of muscle function, so we can start to brainstorm new ways to, measure muscle properties.
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Jenna Monroy: So what are we going to do today? We are going to employ what's called a jigsaw method, and so you are going to be given two different groups today.
Jenna Monroy: First, you're going to be assigned an expert group, and in that expert group, you guys will learn about one single aspect of muscle function. You will become the expert, and you guys will create a Google slide that kind of represents
Jenna Monroy: The main key points of that muscle function.
Jenna Monroy: Later on, you will be assigned to a team, and we will have representatives of each expert group in each one of those teams, and then you will tackle more complex problems in your team.
Jenna Monroy: All right, I'm gonna unshare right now, and I'm gonna draw your attention to our Google Doc. Let me see if I can share the right thing.
Jenna Monroy: Yo here… Okay, so now I'm gonna…
Jenna Monroy: I'm gonna share a Google Doc. Many of you can open it, on your own. Okay, let's go back to this.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, so hopefully you can see my Google Doc. Is that correct?
Jenna Monroy: Yes, I got a… I got a thing. Okay, so the first document page, if you click on this, this is essentially what we just talked about. I gave you sort of the overview. This is what we're doing. And… but then you can see 6 tabs over there, Expert 1 through 6,
Jenna Monroy: that, have different aspects of muscle function. So I'm just gonna click on Expert 1, just to show you what it looks like. So in this group, they're gonna… they're gonna explore muscle and sarcomere organization and structure, and there's a handful of questions there. What is the hierarchical organization of muscle? What is the structure of a muscle sarcomere? How do these structures vary across muscles and species?
Jenna Monroy: And what aspects of muscle structure are not well understood. So, given those questions, together you're going to create one or two Google Slides that you're going to present to the rest of the group. Now, keep in mind, we don't have a ton of time. I'm going to try to keep our presentations to, like, four minutes.
Jenna Monroy: In that folder, I give you some figures, so I'm giving you something to work with, and I'll show you those here in a minute. So…
Jenna Monroy: Include the figures. You can move them around, you can cut them up, you can choose what aspects you want to focus on. Give some bulleted text of those main points that you want to discuss, and maybe come up with a set of questions.
Jenna Monroy: Each person should have a role, so make sure that maybe you have somebody who's the slide organizer, the person who creates the slide, shares it with everybody, and moves things around on the… on the slide. You have people who are researchers. Those are people who might find information that's needed to complete the slide, and then you identify who are going to be the presenters, who are going to be the people who present the slide. Certainly, any and all of you can contribute in that way.
Jenna Monroy: So it's up to you how you want to delegate tasks.
Jenna Monroy: Notice I give you two resources at the bottom. One says sort of the slide, there's actually two slides for Expert 1, I'll show you where that is here in a second, and a related paper. So I'm going to click on this tab. So this is our folder. Do you guys see the folder now?
Jenna Monroy: On my screen.
Jenna Monroy: And what you can see on there, I like the thumbs up, thank you. Sometimes talking into a black box, you never know what you're doing. We can see our Google Doc in here, we see a handful of papers, and then we see a PowerPoint in there. If you click on the PowerPoint, it opens up into Google Slide. You can see the figures that I have provided for you for each of the expert groups. So we have Expert 1 actually has two slides, and these look like typical
Jenna Monroy: figures that you might see in a physiology textbook, and here's… there's a second one for Expert 1. But Expert 2 only has one slide, and so you can see Expert 3 is one slide, then we kind of go down. Everybody has one or two slides that they can include in their presentation.
Jenna Monroy: All right, so the last thing I want to point out is that I also gave a paper associated with that, particular topic. So for the… in the case of muscle and sarcomere structure, you can click on this paper here. Do you see the paper? This is Leroux et al. This is a really cool paper. By no means do I expect anybody to read
Jenna Monroy: the paper in, like, the 15 minutes that you have, but it does have some really cool information. And perhaps for those of you that are a little more advanced, you can look at the introduction, maybe some of the figures that might be relevant to why or how, potentially, those structures might actually vary across different organisms. And in this case, this paper's about insects.
Jenna Monroy: and sarcomere structure in insects. So.
Jenna Monroy: That way, you can address some of those questions about how these structures might vary across different organisms. Okay, I'm going to stop sharing for a second.
Jenna Monroy: Alright.
Jenna Monroy: Let me come back to the group. Now, does everybody know
Jenna Monroy: what they're gonna do. Victoria's gonna give you a… an assignment to one of those expert groups. We're gonna take 15 minutes to create our slide, and then, for those of you who are faculty,
Jenna Monroy: At this point, I would like the students to lead the groups, and the faculty can stay here, but let's imagine that some of you get stuck in your group and you need to call upon a lifeline. That is where a faculty member could join a group, and they could give some insight about what they might need to put into their slide.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, are we ready?
Jenna Monroy: Let's do it!
Victoria Wood: Alright, I have assigned all of you to, breakout rooms. Room 1 will…
Victoria Wood: go to expert… we'll mean Expert 1 tab, Room 2, Expert 2, and so on. You should be able to see which room you're in. If not, I will rename the rooms, or just send out… go in and hop in and let you know which room you're in in a second. Okay, opening rooms now.
Jenna Monroy: Alright.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, so hopefully that works.
Victoria Wood: God.
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Victoria Wood: I might hop into one of the rooms real quick.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Victoria Wood: Okay.
Jenna Monroy: Ugh.
Victoria Wood: Oh, for sure.
CHP233d: Victoria, could you, I mean, we are in a watch party, could you add us?
Victoria Wood: Oh, yes, okay. Moved…
CHP233d: Automatically…
Craig Mcgowan: So I'm gonna stay muted.
Victoria Wood: Yeah, how do I automatically add to you?
Victoria Wood: That's a good question, I know that I can.
CHP233d: Room 5, where we assigned Room 5?
Victoria Wood: Yeah, you're in room 5. For some reason, it's…
Victoria Wood: Making it difficult for me to auto-add you.
Victoria Wood: Oh, they got in. Okay.
Victoria Wood: Third?
Victoria Wood: Okay, I'm gonna hop into Room 1 real quick, just to make sure that you see.
Jenna Monroy: No worries.
Victoria Wood: Alright, I think we're doing good.
Victoria Wood: All the rooms know which room they are? They're…
Jenna Monroy: One thing I forgot to mention, and I think one group is doing it, is that they're… they're saving their Google Slide in the… in the group, so I can see one that says Expert Group 5. I just want to remind them to share their Google Slide in that… in that folder.
Victoria Wood: Okay.
Victoria Wood: Let me… we can put that in the chat.
Victoria Wood: Okay, so how are we doing on time?
Jenna Monroy: You're good. I was thinking 28. At 928, they should, come back to the group.
Victoria Wood: Perfect.
Victoria Wood: Okay, I'll send out, like, a one-minute reminder then, and… 6… 6 minutes or so.
Jenna Monroy: 6 minutes, yeah. I suspect we're gonna, like… Run over in time.
Victoria Wood: We might… the discussion is always fun. It's always a good problem to have if people have more discussion than we plan for.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, I am always a little ambitious, and then I'm like, oh, I'm taking too much time.
Victoria Wood: It's fine. I like this. This setup is great, especially for the first workshop. You were doing great, because.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, thanks.
Victoria Wood: know each other, and… Thank you.
Jenna Monroy: And I want the students to… oh, there looks like there's a group that's a little confused on how to make something work.
Jenna Monroy: Do they need some help? I see…
Victoria Wood: Yeah…
Jenna Monroy: Oh.
Jenna Monroy: I'm not exactly sure. They say they're behind, but can we… Hope?
Victoria Wood: Where are you seeing this?
Jenna Monroy: Oh, that was from Craig, but it went straight to me.
Victoria Wood: Oh.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, let me see if I can… .
Victoria Wood: Do you want to join that room? Craig is in there.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, what group is it, is he in?
Victoria Wood: Craig is not actually in a group.
Jenna Monroy: Oh.
Jenna Monroy: Maybe… oh, he's in… he's in 2.
Victoria Wood: And two, okay, can I, can I send you to 2?
Jenna Monroy: Sure.
Victoria Wood: Okay. Me.
Jenna Monroy: Oh, okay.
Jenna Monroy: They didn't seem to need me at all, so I'm not really sure what… they all looked weird, they were like, what are you doing here?
Jenna Monroy: So… and you hate to, like, you know, interfere and be like, hello? It's like popping into someone's conversation, and they're like, what are you doing?
Victoria Wood: Yeah, why are you here right now?
Jenna Monroy: Why are you here? So, I'm not really sure, and…
Jenna Monroy: I don't want to interfere with anything.
Jenna Monroy: Boom.
Jenna Monroy: I think students do a much better job. I was curious, so… I'm so clueless, what's the watch party? Is that… allows you to, like, just pop in?
Victoria Wood: So the watch parties, a couple of our universities have, like, several teams that are… they just choose. They, like, book a,
Victoria Wood: Like, a conference room or something.
Jenna Monroy: I see.
Victoria Wood: Yeah, the same.
Victoria Wood: Yeah, so…
Victoria Wood: It makes breakout room things a bit more difficult, but they seem to make it work usually, so… Okay.
Jenna Monroy: Oh, because there's so many of them all in the same room.
Victoria Wood: Yeah,
Jenna Monroy: I can understand that, I see.
Jenna Monroy: I see, that's why I'm a little confused. I think he was more asking about the watch party, and less about, thing, and clearly I'm clueless about watch parties.
Victoria Wood: I should've… yeah, that was something… I kind of forgot that groups do that, even though I encourage them to it.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, I… you know, I am not well-versed in Zoom, and I find them to be…
Jenna Monroy: Really frustrating for establishing conversation and discussion, unless you have a small group.
Victoria Wood: Yeah.
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Jenna Monroy: Boom.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, I have a set… 26… okay.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, and I'm certain the students are probably going well beyond what I'm expecting them to do, because there's just not a lot of time.
Joe Thompson: Hey guys.
Joe Thompson: Sorry, my camera's not working.
Jenna Monroy: No, it's totally fine.
Victoria Wood: Hello, how are you?
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Joe Thompson: I'm doing well, Victoria, how are you?
Victoria Wood: Doing well, yeah.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Victoria Wood: Are you at…
Joe Thompson: working out great, by the way. Yeah, we're up at the Darling Center, and so she's… she's,
Joe Thompson: She's really very, very, very, very, very good.
Victoria Wood: Good. Glad to hear it.
Victoria Wood: Did you guys head up this week? Is this your first week at the Darling Center?
Joe Thompson: It's my second week, but it's her first.
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Joe Thompson: So she and her parents came out early, I got a chance to meet them.
Joe Thompson: Yeah, it's their first time… all of their first times in Maine, and so…
Joe Thompson: I think they also wanted to make sure that their… their baby was not going to be in a really bad situation, which I get.
Jenna Monroy: Oh, that's nice.
Joe Thompson: Which I get. So, you know,
Joe Thompson: she's getting a good main experience, like, right now, it's drizzling and about, like, 58 degrees.
Joe Thompson: But a couple days ago, it was sunny and 80, so she's… she's getting the full range of the way things are here.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Victoria Wood: Great.
Jenna Monroy: Where's she coming from?
Joe Thompson: She… well, she's, been living in Houston since she was 11.
Joe Thompson: But she most recently got, Master's in Biomedical Engineering, from Brown.
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Joe Thompson: Before then, she did an undergrad in biomedical engineering at Texas A&M.
Jenna Monroy: Oh, that's excellent. Okay.
Joe Thompson: I didn't realize how big Texas A&M was. She says it's 80,000 undergrads.
Jenna Monroy: It is so gigantic, yeah.
Joe Thompson: Wow.
Jenna Monroy: My husband did a year in that at A&M when he was, you know, 18 years old, and then he promptly transferred.
Joe Thompson: I'm gonna guess you could… it would be possible to literally never speak personally to one of your faculty members in a situation like that.
Jenna Monroy: And imagine the, yeah, the class sizes are just so large.
Victoria Wood: Alright, I set the one-minute warning about, like, 45 seconds ago, I guess.
Jenna Monroy: Okay, sounds good, and they'll all pop in. Okay, and then we'll probably just go in order, because it makes it easier. Right now, I'm only seeing two Google Groups, like, Google Slides. I see Expert Group 2 and Expert Group 5 in the folder. Do you see more than I do?
Victoria Wood: I do not, so they might just not have put it in that folder yet. We'll tell them to make sure it's copied over there.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, they can… they can present their slide without having shared it, but, yeah, eventually they should share their… share their slide.
Victoria Wood: Okay. Alright, let me go ahead and close rooms now.
Victoria Wood: It gives them, like, a few seconds just to… Join in.
Jenna Monroy: Wrap stuff up.
Victoria Wood: So they're all gonna go into their same workout or breakout rooms.
Victoria Wood: For the next…
Jenna Monroy: No, it should be a mix, right? So, you have experts 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, and now, honestly, I think we could create 4 rooms, but it should have 6 people. I honestly don't know how many people we had, but I kind of assumed somewhere like 24. And so, do you see what I'm saying? Is that you should take 1 from 1, 1 from 2, 1 from 3, 1 from 4.
Victoria Wood: Does that make sense? Yeah.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, welcome back, everybody!
Jenna Monroy: All right, it was a little quick. I know 15 minutes, you're like, I didn't actually finish everything that I wanted to do. But hopefully you guys have stuff to say, and I'm gonna try to keep us on task, so… because we don't have a ton of time. So,
Jenna Monroy: I'm gonna ask Expert Group 1, have you identified a presenter, and would you like to share your slide, present your slide for us?
Adwait Mane: I'm the presenter for Expert Group 1.
Adwait Mane: So… I will try to share my slide now.
Adwait Mane: Let me get into… Okay.
Adwait Mane: Share screen.
Adwait Mane: Mask.
Adwait Mane: And… make sure.
Adwait Mane: Do you see my screen now?
Jenna Monroy: Yes.
Isabel Munoz Orozco: Okay.
Adwait Mane: Great, so, we are talking about muscle and sarcomere organization and structure.
Adwait Mane: So here we see a single muscle fiber, which, interestingly, can span the entire length of a muscle, I believe.
Adwait Mane: And, like, it's very different from most cells, it's just, it can be very long,
Adwait Mane: And, the smallest unit of a muscle is a sarcomere. It has…
Adwait Mane: The typical length is 2 to 2.5 micron, and this is pretty consistent across organisms.
Adwait Mane: Both ranging from insects to elephants, I believe. You can correct me if I'm wrong.
Adwait Mane: And it's got some… some of the structures in it are described here.
Adwait Mane: So this is called a ZDisk. The ZDisk has a…
Adwait Mane: filament coming out of it, which is the… I believe, the thin filament, yeah, that's the green one. And then…
Adwait Mane: In the middle, there's a,
Adwait Mane: M line, this is called the M line, and then there's another filament called the thick filament coming out of it.
Adwait Mane: Go to the next slide.
Adwait Mane: Yeah, this shows a more detailed view of the sarcomere structure.
Adwait Mane: ZDisc, M-Line, thick filament, Tin Filament.
Adwait Mane: Actually, I'm using my mouse to point.
Jenna Monroy: You…
Adwait Mane: Good to see? Okay, good.
Jenna Monroy: Yes.
Adwait Mane: then, the M line, And so this is a, close-up of the thick filament. It has these…
Adwait Mane: These myosin heads, which are also called cross bridges, Which, attached to the thin filament.
Adwait Mane: So you can see that here.
Adwait Mane: So, when the muscle is activated, the cross bridge is attached to the thin filament, and they…
Adwait Mane: they pull on them, and what I have learned is that they actually kind of have a swing phase as well, so they're running on the thin filament as they… as the muscle contracts.
Adwait Mane: Another important structure is the… Is this part called Titan?
Adwait Mane: Which… spans… which, connects the ZDesk to the M line.
Adwait Mane: And I believe that is responsible for the passive stiffness of muscle. So when a muscle is not activated, and the crossbidges are not engaged, if you stretch it, it's the tight end that's giving… providing that elastic
Adwait Mane: Resistance.
Adwait Mane: That's all the time we had for the purpose of making slides.
Adwait Mane: So I'll try to describe some of the questions about things we do not know.
Adwait Mane: So… the Hill model is… Good at predicting static muscle function.
Adwait Mane: But it doesn't match with a lot of…
Adwait Mane: The data we observe in dynamic muscle function.
Adwait Mane: And, we believe that… the… this element, Titan, this filament,
Adwait Mane: Plays a role which we don't fully understand, so that's ongoing research.
Adwait Mane: Yeah, that's one of the things we don't know, like, how… how are muscles tuning their stiffness?
Adwait Mane: In dynamic, conditions.
Adwait Mane: Yeah, that's one of the questions.
Jenna Monroy: Great. Does anyone have any questions?
Jenna Monroy: So one thing I was struck by, I don't see any hands, is that, sarcomere length can actually vary pretty
Jenna Monroy: pretty wildly in, in invertebrates. And, much more so than that of a vertebrate muscle. And, and, you know, I'll throw the question out there. Does anybody know about, sort of, the variation in sarcomere length?
Jenna Monroy: You know, invertebrate muscle.
Amulya Kadaba: I do know about superelongation and obliquely striated muscles, so one of the, animals that we're working with is bloodworms, and they say that for some obliquely striated muscles, they can elongate to maybe 5 times or 6 times their length.
Jenna Monroy: Wow.
Jenna Monroy: And they still maintain force, too, right?
Amulya Kadaba: Right.
Jenna Monroy: And so that's super impressive. So I, you know, one of the things to take from this is that, while the structure may be really similar, the length can vary, and it does seem like Titan is this ruler, but we can change the length of our thick and thin filaments in ways that maybe vertebrate muscles cannot.
Jenna Monroy: And so, it's one comparison that you can ask, is how that impacts the function of the muscle.
Jenna Monroy: Are there any other questions or comments about that?
Jenna Monroy: Alright, I'm gonna keep us moving forward.
Jenna Monroy: The… you can unshare, or… yeah, and then we can allow.
Adwait Mane: Thank you.
Jenna Monroy: 2… Tell us something about their…
Jenna Monroy: Better slide.
Lauren Infantino: I can chair for our group. Let me just pull up our slides.
Lauren Infantino: Alright.
Lauren Infantino: So, we had, excitation-contraction coupling, and kind of, like, questions about how this differs across species, and sort of what are the questions that we still have that we don't really understand about ECC. So,
Lauren Infantino: it might be important to start with what ECC is, and it's
Lauren Infantino: what I… because I don't really know too much about it, but from what I understand, it's basically from the start of an action potential at a muscle cell all the way to the actual mechanical contraction that's happening at the sarcomere. So it's everything that happens in between there. A lot of it is, like.
Lauren Infantino: dealing with molecular kinetics of calcium cycling in and out of the cell, from action potentials. So we kind of start with the depolarization signal here that sends sodium through the cell.
Lauren Infantino: Depolarizes that cell, and that leads to calcium influx into the cell.
Lauren Infantino: calcium binds to troponin, and then you get cross-bridge cycling, and then it can be reuptaken by this, like, ryanidine receptor, comes back into the cell, and then you kind of get this on and off of, like, contraction that occurs. So that's kind of the main idea
Lauren Infantino: from what ECC is, it's, pretty short time in terms of how long it takes from a depolarizing signal to get to an actual, like, shortening of the sarcomere.
Lauren Infantino: And so, kind of the questions that we had was…
Lauren Infantino: Like, how does it affect muscle force, how does it vary across species, and what is not really well understood, so our group was able to look at this a little bit.
Lauren Infantino: Kind of the second two questions, more or less, which is how does it differ across organisms, and what are the challenges that, people who study ECC still face. So, one of the things that we saw was
Lauren Infantino: variation, basically, and sarcoplasmic reticulum density can influence the frequency at which you're contracting, and variation in the molecular machinery can lead to variation in the ECC kinetics, so if you have higher density of rinidine receptors.
Lauren Infantino: Maybe receptors that have a higher affinity,
Lauren Infantino: for calcium, that can all lead to variation in how long ECC can take.
Lauren Infantino: And so, maybe some of the challenges, that are not all encapsulating, but some of the challenges that we noted was, consistency in methodology for identifying calcium concentrations. I think this… because you're working on a pretty small scale, like, molecular scale, I think there was a lot of…
Lauren Infantino: complications early on, but as we've kind of grown technologically-wise, there's a lot better, like, fluoroscopy, methods to, like, identifying influx into the cell, and then
Lauren Infantino: uptake, but I think there… from what we saw, there was still maybe contention between how different labs are doing it, how you can kind of identify the differences between already present calcium that's just floating within the cell, and then actual calcium that is implicated in, like, actually the mechanical, contraction. So I think
Lauren Infantino: consistency in methodology was one of the challenges that maybe additional tech can, like, kind of ground. And then one interesting one that I found was, IPCS-derived skeletal myocytes and their ECC.
Lauren Infantino: does it kind of differ from normal skeletal muscle? Because I think there's a kind of therapeutic trend going into, like, pluripotent-derived stem cells, and so trying to understand how
Lauren Infantino: skeletal muscle stem cells and their ECC different from normal stem cells, obviously, was something that hasn't been really answered or fully fledged out.
Lauren Infantino: And I think that that is all we had.
Jenna Monroy: That's excellent. I do not know much about the iPSC-derived myocytes. Those are quite interesting. And you're right, like, are they actually the same as what you may find in actual muscles? Does anybody have any questions about that? I think that was great.
Adwait Mane: Yeah, I have a question.
Adwait Mane: nice work in the short time frame. I was just curious, what is the time scale of this whole…
Adwait Mane: Process from excitation to contraction.
Lauren Infantino: I honestly don't know the exact timescale. I would say, like, on the order of…
Lauren Infantino: maybe, like, milliseconds? But I'm not too sure, maybe someone could correct me.
Jenna Monroy: Well, think about, like, a twitch in a muscle. If you guys work on muscle twitches, you know, they can occur in just, you know, your time to force development can occur in just a few milliseconds, and in some really fast muscles, it can be a few milliseconds. For some, it's more like 20 to 50 milliseconds. So, certainly, you're releasing calcium into the cell from the sarcoplasmic reticulum.
Jenna Monroy: One thing that I might ask, too, is about… so we often talk about force development and the release of calcium. What do you know about the rate of calcium uptake? And that would be associated with relaxation.
Lauren Infantino: what I at least minorly know is that it's a lot slower than the rate of force development, maybe, like, sometimes double.
Lauren Infantino: I'm not as… I'm not very sure as to why, though.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah. Does anybody else know?
Skylar Jay Taylor: I think usually it's slower to prevent, like, a retwitch, like, of activating the same muscle.
Jenna Monroy: similar? Like, thinking about, like, an action potential that might have some absolute refractory period, potentially. One thing to think about is that… so, and we'll… I think we're gonna hear this in a minute, is, we'll learn about summation of force in… in a muscle.
Jenna Monroy: Well, relaxation is associated with that uptake into… back into the sarcoplasmic recticulum, and it's associated with what we call our circa pumps. Circa just stands for sarcoplasmic endo…
Jenna Monroy: Right, endoplasmic recticulum calcium ATPase. But it takes a lot of energy, you know, it takes ATP to
Jenna Monroy: pump that calcium back into the sarcoplasmic reticulum, and those have their own kinetics. They have their own rate, they're often quite slow, and you can upregulate the number of circa pumps that are on your SR, but to increase the rate at which you go. But keep in mind that's always a little bit slower, and as you pointed out, is that the frequency of contraction is dependent on how quickly you can
Jenna Monroy: Increase force, but also how quickly you can decrease it.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, I'm gonna keep us moving forward. Let's hear from Group 3.
Hedyeh Teymouri: I'm sorry, I just want to add this. Also, all of these processes are so related to the type of the muscles that we have. I mean, fires to each or slow to each.
Jenna Monroy: Yes, that is quite correct, yeah. So all these things vary with what we call, sort of, fast and slow twitch muscles. Yeah, thank you.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, let's move to Group 3.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: Awesome. So for this part, we kind of divided it up by 3 parts, low frequency, medium frequency, and high frequency, but just in part, you can see here for the 1 time per second, 2 times per second, there's no summation, so just kind of meaning that, the muscle
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: Completely relaxes between the stimuli. It does show, like, those individual muscle twitches.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And then going over to, like, the middle part, the summation, just kind of meaning that
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: stimuli does arrive before the muscle can fully relax, causing the contractions to run on top of each other. I know we kind of put here in medium frequency, the muscle switches begin to sum up to incomplete setness, and that's kind of here on this part. Just kind of meaning that there's rapid, successive
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: stimulation results and a peak force that, the plate is visible with. But you can see there's, like, maybe minor relaxation, ripples.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And over here on the high frequency, we kind of just…
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: Came up with the conclusion that those are kind of high simulation frequencies, meaning that the individual twitches do begin to kind of blend into one another.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: Kind of making one smooth, sustained contraction.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And going over to this one, I think there was somebody else in our group that wanted to… they found this from a different paper, but I think they kind of wanted to speak on this one.
GT watch party: Oh, well, this is just adding a little bit to what we already heard. I thought that this figure shows really nicely how these individual twitches may sum up at individual… Sorry, in intermediate range of the,
GT watch party: stimulus frequency. And if we look at the magnitude of the force developed as a summation of these tweets is…
GT watch party: In the lower range of the stimulus rate, it is, monotonically increasing.
GT watch party: With the stimulus frequency, and it is actually at some point after some frequency.
GT watch party: Err, yep.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And then, just to kind of answer the questions, how does the frequency of simulation affect the force output of a muscle, we came up with the idea that the increased stimulation frequency does increase the force output of a muscle.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And with higher frequency, twitches overlap. How do these processes vary across muscles and species? Force-frequency relationships do change. Different species have different locomotor demands.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: Some animals do have slow oxidative fibers, and others have fast glycolic fibers that later produce a large amount of force faster, but it is quicker to fatigue.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And then, what are the limitations of this relationship? The maximum amount of possible forces constrained by muscle properties, which does mean that fused tetanus has a fixed upper bound for force generation, and the frequency of stimulation is also physiologically constrained by the rate at which muscle activation is possible.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: And then, what aspects of muscle activation aren't well understood. Understanding from the article that was given, was the, transmitter signal, so we do understand that physical muscle pulling, does dictate the sarcomere size.
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: But the internal chemical messengers that translate those mechanical forces into a growth command, aren't fully understood. So motor recruitment versus firing rates,
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: kind of how those interact to regulate force production. And that's pretty much what we were able to do within
Brandon Jesus Guereque Torres: For 15 minutes.
Jenna Monroy: Excellent, thank you. Here, if you want to unshare for a second, does anybody have, any questions about this?
Jenna Monroy: So I'm gonna ask a little bit about, so this was a… this is a measurement that you take from a whole muscle, and so… and whereas the previous group talked about molecular mechanisms, can you think of how
Jenna Monroy: The excitation-contraction coupling that they mentioned in the last group relates to what you presented, and with the force-frequency relationship.
GT watch party: Yeah, I think I can answer that question. So, in that first figure that we were looking at, we have sort of a quick up spike, and then a slow sort of exponential decrease, and that is coming from that relationship we just talked about, where it takes less time to activate the muscle than it does to deactivate and get that calcium
GT watch party: Uptake happening.
GT watch party: And the fact that there's a longer amount of cooldown period makes it so that when those two things overlap, we get that summation property.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, so if you had another stimulus come in, more calcium's gonna get released, and they're just gonna add the force on top of the previous twitch.
Jenna Monroy: Excellent. So, things that I'm trying to emphasize is thinking across chaos there, right? Where we're thinking about the molecular mechanisms that might underlie the muscle property that you're measuring. So, in the force-frequency relationship, we're measuring it from the muscle, but we kind of have to think about all those molecular mechanisms that are taking place.
Jenna Monroy: The other thing that I might, ask is do you… can you think of a limitation of that type of measurement? So you can go in, you can measure these…
Jenna Monroy: you know, you get… stimulate the muscle at a certain frequency, and you get this nice force from profile, then you'd increase the frequency, and you'd do it again. What do you know about how those measurements are taken, and is there a limitation when you try to consider an actual animal?
Jenna Monroy: Does anybody record EMG?
GT watch party: Yeah, I think that the limitation with the way that we record EMG, at least in my labs, is it's a service EMG, so we're not measuring a singular muscle fiber, we're getting just a sort of general difference between two rough points, but you aren't able to get
GT watch party: Fiber-level activation information that way.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, it becomes difficult to compare what you're measuring at your EMG to this
Jenna Monroy: whole muscle sort of preparation. And the one thing that I was getting at was sort of, we often just stimulate at a single frequency, say 30 Hz, and then we activate the muscle, and they're… and if you notice, those are activated at isometrically, so they're not changing length.
Jenna Monroy: And we'll talk a little bit about length here in a minute, and… and then they change the frequency, and let's stimulate it at 100 Hz. But when I'm…
Jenna Monroy: when the nervous system activates our muscle, it can change things. This is what we mean by rate coding, is that it might increase the frequency, and then decrease the frequency, and it's tuned to whatever it is that it's actually doing. And in fact, I study something called doublet potentiation, where sometimes you can actually activate the muscle really rapidly, and then you decrease the frequency. And you can see this in the EMG, and we can try to replicate
Jenna Monroy: it in the lab, and it changes the force output of the muscle.
Jenna Monroy: So, things to consider is some of our measurements are often kind of limited and don't necessarily represent what's actually happening in the muscle. Or, sorry, in the animal. Okay, we gotta keep going forward. Let's hear from group 4, right? We're in Group 4.
Spencer Berv: I'm gonna present the first figure, if I can figure out how to share my screen.
Spencer Berv: Shoot, it won't let me share my screen.
Spencer Berv: Sorry, one moment.
Jenna Monroy: Alright.
Jenna Monroy: I don't know, Victoria, do you know what's going on there?
Victoria Wood: Not sure, sometimes…
Spencer Berv: Can someone else from my group just share it, and then I can just speak over it?
Jenna Monroy: works.
Andrew M Thornton: I can't. I'm on my phone, so I can't share.
Katrina Moore: I can share, just give me a second.
Wonbin Bae: Well, I can do that.
Spencer Berv: Awesome.
Wonbin Bae: Oh.
Spencer Berv: So, the first figure is a pretty generic, passive versus active force curve, with, the passive, obviously, is more dependent on the elastic structure, so that'll be mostly titan, and then also the extracellular matrix, and so…
Spencer Berv: Obviously, as you're at these lower lengths, you won't get a lot of force, but then as you stretch it out, those elastic components play a much bigger role, and you have this exponential curve. Whereas the active force curve is more dependent on cross-bridge cycling, so you have
Spencer Berv: this sort of peak, which is often referred to as L0, so the optimal length of the muscle and the force-length relationship, and that'll be the, like, most active cross bridges. And obviously, if you're at a shorter length or a higher length, you'll have less cross bridges, or you'll have too much overlap, which decreases the efficiency of it.
Spencer Berv: And one of the, sort of, questions we had based on that, so I work in Dr. Monroy's lab, and we study
Spencer Berv: mice that have a chunk of their Titan cut out, and obviously that would change the force-length relationship, and one of the questions is, like, how would, you know, if the elastic component like Titan, if that was altered, how would the force-length relationship change in this graph?
Jenna Monroy: Someone else from that group wanna also…
Andrew M Thornton: I… I can do the next slide, if… but I'll need… okay, perfect. Okay, so…
Andrew M Thornton: This figure is really interesting because the top figure, A, is comparing the force-length relationship between vertebrates and then invertebrates in B.
Andrew M Thornton: And some of the key takeaways of this are that the inverted U relationship of the force-length curve stays the same, so there's gonna be some optimal length, and if you lengthen past that point, it's gonna be, it's gonna have worse contractile mechanics, and same thing if you shorten it.
Andrew M Thornton: But there are some, interesting…
Andrew M Thornton: Points about this, which is that…
Andrew M Thornton: The amount of relative lengthening or shortening?
Andrew M Thornton: is different depending on species, so I think it's the… the mouse limb…
Andrew M Thornton: The red line in A is very interesting because it only shortens to…
Andrew M Thornton: like.95 of its relative optimal length. And so, that could be indicative of…
Andrew M Thornton: its optimal length being in an already very shortened position, there's not much more shortening it can do, or there's some other limitation there. So…
Andrew M Thornton: There is some variation between species on where that
Andrew M Thornton: optimal length might be. The way they normalize this graph is
Andrew M Thornton: A little frustrating to me personally, because…
Andrew M Thornton: I would want the x-axis to be… Relative overlap.
Andrew M Thornton: Of, the sarcomere.
Jenna Monroy: Just a second.
Andrew M Thornton: Because when you… right now, it's normalized to its optimal length, which is normalizing to optimal force, so your x-axis is normalized to your y-axis, which I… I think you could see a lot more interesting things if you didn't do that.
Andrew M Thornton: But you can still see some really interesting trends,
Andrew M Thornton: And then, some of the limitations, that you have when
Andrew M Thornton: trying to explain all contractile mechanics just through force velocity and force length, is that when you actually put
Andrew M Thornton: muscles in more realistic conditions, like Dr. Daley has done some perturbed locomotion studies, making work loops out of those, and there's some inconsistencies between what you would expect to see and what you actually see. And so, it opens
Andrew M Thornton: Room for other explanatory, factors, like
Andrew M Thornton: the tension inherent in, like, the extracellular matrix, an active role for Titan in contractions, and then different calcium uptake or removal speeds, depending on your force length or position on the force-velocity curve.
Jenna Monroy: Nice.
Jenna Monroy: Thank you. Are there any questions?
Jenna Monroy: I'm always struck at how variable… oh, go ahead, go ahead.
GT watch party: Well, I have a very naive question about buffers.
Jenna Monroy: Yes.
GT watch party: curve. The…
GT watch party: Coming from really nice perspective, I feel like it is always beneficial to have a wide force length curve.
GT watch party: like, it would be nice if you have a wide range of population where you can produce, like, significant forests. So, what would be the reason why benefit of having a shallow curb for an animal? Or is there the cost of having a wide curb?
Jenna Monroy: This is a good question. Does anybody have any thoughts about it?
Andrew M Thornton: I have a guess, which is… I don't know any situation where it's better to have a really narrow
Andrew M Thornton: Force length curve.
Andrew M Thornton: But I think if you have…
Andrew M Thornton: Tendon properties that allow you to activate muscles in mostly isometric conditions, then it doesn't matter how wide, your force-length curve is, because you're mostly going to be acting at that relative length in isometric conditions.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, I would agree that there are some muscles that barely change their length, and it ends the tendons that do the work. So, so they can stay mostly isometric, and their… their force length nerves can be quite narrow. But, as we pointed out, those,
Jenna Monroy: Invertebrates, like the annelids and some of the insects, have really large sarcomeres, and their force length curves just keep going for a really long time, and it allows them to maintain force over a really large range of lengths.
Jenna Monroy: So, I don't know, honestly, the cost of that really long thing. I forget who it was who studies the blood worms. Do you have anything to tell us about it?
Amulya Kadaba: Sorry, I was muted.
Amulya Kadaba: I actually don't know much, I just started the project, but I guess so many things that I do know is that the super elongation that they have with the broad source length curve, they have a specific purpose, and the PI that I work with, he…
Amulya Kadaba: Specifically saw that in squids as well, and they said that they saw it in the tentacles, so the tentacles would stretch out super far for the prey strike, and that was why they had the broad clay.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Jenna Monroy: Oh, and if you guys had seen in the last slide, there was the chameleon, and so the chameleon can function at really short lengths on the ascending limb of its, force-length curve, and that is because they're considered to be super contracting, so it means that they can get really short and still maintain, maintain force. In fact, the hypothesis is that the
Jenna Monroy: thick filaments actually slide through holes in the Z disc, and then interact with the thin filament in the adjacent sarcomere. And while they haven't totally seen all of that, it really is mind-boggling to know that they could get that short and still maintain force.
Jenna Monroy: In ways that other vertebrates cannot, and it's because they can extend their tongues out, but they're actually… they have to maintain force even as they contract back into the mouth.
Jenna Monroy: So there are a lot of cool little changes that are taking place in these organisms that allow them to either maintain force over a large range of lengths, or on one side of the curve, either on the ascending or the descending limb.
Jenna Monroy: One other thing to point out, right, and I think you've already mentioned this, is that the force length curve is a static property, right? And you've already mentioned about work loops and other ways to really get at dynamic muscle function, which some of these tests, like the force length, and we'll learn about the force-velocity relationship, just really don't capture, because they're… you collect those data in these really static ways, when the muscle's not changing.
Jenna Monroy: in length. So, clearly, the force of the muscle's gonna change if we stretch it, or if we lengthen, or if we shorten it.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, let's move forward, let's go to Group 5.
Carissa J Mallonee: Okay, I'm gonna try to share my screen here, and I didn't have time to look at our graphs, so, bear with me.
Carissa J Mallonee: Did you just go to slideshow and then hit share? Is.
Jenna Monroy: I think you have to hit share and sludge, and then shine.
Carissa J Mallonee: show.
Jenna Monroy: Or at least…
Victoria Wood: Yeah, so the actual share is in the Zoom window, the…
Carissa J Mallonee: Yeah. Let's see here. Let's see if I can figure this out.
Victoria Wood: You have yours in the folder, right? I can also share it for you.
Victoria Wood: If that's helpful.
Jenna Monroy: Would that work, Carissa?
Jenna Monroy: Oh, she's got it. Okay.
Carissa J Mallonee: I'm sorry, I didn't know I had re-muted myself. Okay, does that look good for everybody?
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, that looks great.
Carissa J Mallonee: Okay, so like I said, I didn't have time to look at the graphs, but, so, if somebody in my group can chime in and help me, that would be great. But, anyway, okay, so, the force-velocity relationship of muscle, if you don't know, so,
Carissa J Mallonee: as,
Carissa J Mallonee: The faster a muscle has to contract, the less forces it's able to produce, basically, is what it says.
Carissa J Mallonee: And this force-velocity relationship does vary across muscles and species. It depends on the fiber type, whether it's a slow twitch or a fast twitch fiber, and which I think is shown in this graph down here that I didn't get to really look at, but, you can see in these graphs there are, let's see.
Carissa J Mallonee: Bat wings, fast twitch muscles of mice, and slow twitch muscles of mice, so…
Carissa J Mallonee: I'll go back to this. But it also depends on, the fiber length, which we already talked about a little bit, and the pronation angle. It also depends on the operating frequency of the muscle, and,
Carissa J Mallonee: The type of contractions.
Carissa J Mallonee: And so, yes, this varies across species, too, as we saw in this figure here.
Carissa J Mallonee: Let's see, let me go back to this.
Carissa J Mallonee: And how does this relate to the swing and cross bridge theory? Well, it depends on the rate of, basically ATP cycling rates, the rate of myosin detachment and attachment, and force proportional to the number of cross bridges that are attached simultaneously.
Carissa J Mallonee: But what this doesn't take into account, is our history-dependent effects. It ignores the role of Titan, and it's based… these, force-velocity experiments are based on Hill models.
Carissa J Mallonee: Which were, these experiments were done under maximal activation, based on isotonic conditions, and as most biological movements typically are under submaximal conditions.
Carissa J Mallonee: And then… Let's see… I didn't look at this one yet, but, let's see…
Roger Chen: I…
Roger Chen: I made this, or, like, I explained this plot so I can just talk about this, but,
Roger Chen: Basically, this ex… This plot shows, like, power as a relationship, like, on… overlaid on top of some arbitrary force, force-velocity graph. And the force-velocity plot, like, it shows this,
Roger Chen: this,
Roger Chen: like, the downward trend that you see with pretty much every single other muscle. And then, because power is a product of force times velocity, you're… like, the max velocity would be somewhere in the middle, where both, force and velocity is relatively high.
Roger Chen: And it tapers off, or, like, it decreases a lot, at the end. So that's kind of what the spot shows.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, are there some questions or comments?
Jenna Monroy: You guys can unshare your screen so we can see everybody.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, I think you guys hit the main points. The point is, is that clearly, you know, it can change. It's focused on shortening, right? And so shortening velocity, it doesn't tell us much about lengthening. And… and as you guys pointed out, it's,
Jenna Monroy: It, you know, it's a quasi-static sort of measurement.
Jenna Monroy: And… and so it's under these isotonic conditions, your muscles maximally activated, which doesn't necessarily represent natural movements. And so, hopefully we're getting a theme here, that the properties that we measure under these highly controlled conditions, they don't necessarily represent what, what's actually, happening in an animal.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, any other comments?
Jenna Monroy: Let's move on to Group 6!
Jenna Monroy: Okay.
Taylor Bourque: Our group didn't actually choose a presenter, but I can share my screen. I think we're just gonna work off of…
Taylor Bourque: Oh, I'm sorry.
Taylor Bourque: Just gotta figure out… Where that is… Cheer.
Taylor Bourque: So yeah, we were just working off of the, figure provided in the slide.
Taylor Bourque: And we touched on briefly… is this… is my screen shared for everyone?
Jenna Monroy: Yes.
Taylor Bourque: So we were just talking about how the figure shows the different panacea angles, and so we were talking about the difference mainly between what it means to have, like, a very parallel muscle versus a highly panated muscle.
Taylor Bourque: And so, if there's a very parallel muscle, that means that the muscles kind of run along the length of the tendon, and all the fibers are parallel, and it allows for more sarcomeres in series, which means that it can shorten a lot, and it can shorten faster, whereas
Taylor Bourque: If you have a lot of parallel muscles, it kind of restricts the speed of contraction.
Taylor Bourque: Of each individual fiber, but that restriction allows for more fibers to be packed into a smaller unit, which allows for more force output, since there's just a lot more overlap between the thick and…
Taylor Bourque: thin filaments, and so we were kind of talking about how there's a trade-off between maximum force output and speed of contraction, which I think the, Expert Group 5 covered nicely.
Taylor Bourque: And as for the differences between
Taylor Bourque: species. I think, I heard, like, the watch party was discussing that a bit, so I don't know if they want to jump in for that part.
Mines watch party: I can chime in for that a bit.
Mines watch party: I didn't get the chance to fully go over all the figures in the paper, but in…
Mines watch party: Figure 4 of the paper, they compare the cross-section area and the length of the muscles, and they looked at multiple different frog species, but broke them up into swimmers, jumpers, and walker hoppers. And what's interesting is, for the
Mines watch party: as the length of their muscle increased, so did the cross-section area, and that was the opposite for both the jumpers and walker hoppers, which I think is very interesting and shows, how when there's different function needed for the muscles, like swimming for these species.
Mines watch party: Then the structure will differ also.
Jenna Monroy: Nice. Does anybody else want to add to that?
Jenna Monroy: I like this because here we're talking about whole muscle structure, and in the previous group, they were talking about, sort of, muscle properties, and combined, they can impact, you know, the rate at which a muscle can shorten, and the force that they can produce, and so again, we need to be thinking about muscle properties across different scales, from their tendon muscle organization and architecture, thinking about individual muscle properties
Jenna Monroy: like, you know, we were talking about fiber types, or the rate of myosin attachment and detachment rates, and then thinking about those molecular mechanisms that underlie, sort of, the release and uptake of calcium. So we can start to see how we have to address all different levels of biological organization to kind of get at these
Jenna Monroy: tuned properties of muscle for whatever, you know, behavior that they're trying to perform. Hopping, running, jumping, feeding, all these different things.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, this is great! I hope you guys are learning things, right? It's helping you kind of explain things maybe you knew, maybe you got a little better of a chance to, understand it. So.
Jenna Monroy: I, of course, over, you know, budgeted or under-budgeted my time, but I want to take the remaining time to kind of tell you a little bit about what I do. You guys have already mentioned a little bit about Titan, and… and maybe we can discuss as a group, now that we're all experts and different, to kind of think about the role of Titan in muscle, as we've kind of
Jenna Monroy: brought it up in different ways. So I'm gonna go back and share my screen again.
Jenna Monroy: Let's see, so let me go here…
Jenna Monroy: Oh, no, I'm gonna go here, hold on. Share, and then let me go here, and…
Jenna Monroy: Okay, do you guys see my toad feeding?
Jenna Monroy: Yes, okay, I got this. Okay, so I think in our explanations of these fundamental principles of muscle function, I think we all kind of said, oh yeah, we can measure these things in muscle, but
Jenna Monroy: what we are all struck by is that certain properties that we've measured really don't accurately predict natural dynamic movements, and so we're missing something. Our understanding of muscle function is incomplete. And this story actually started with me in… when I was a graduate student, when I studied feeding in frogs. And so what you're looking at here is a
Jenna Monroy: Toad feeding on a cricket. And this is done in a high-speed video.
Jenna Monroy: And what I want you to pay attention to is that they open their mouths really fast, and really fast, which then flips the tongue out of the mouth really fast, kind of like a whip. And so, it is…
Jenna Monroy: those jaw muscles are depressor mandibular muscles that contract really fast, really rapidly, to open the mouth fast. And when you measure it, you get these enormous power outputs, and they don't have any tendons. And one of the things that really challenged us in our research is where do they get this enormous higher power output?
Jenna Monroy: And over the years, you might have thought that this was unique to toads, and it was something special, but over the years, many researchers, including yourselves and your mentors, have found many examples of organisms that exhibit power output that far exceeds what we predict as being the maximum, because it's defined by our force-velocity relationship, which doesn't take into account
Jenna Monroy: viscoelasticity, right? And so we know that muscles are viscoelastic, and as you guys kind of were alluding to, we know that Titan plays a role in that viscoelasticity.
Jenna Monroy: And the other thing that you guys have pointed out is that muscles aren't static, so these properties of viscos, you know.
Jenna Monroy: force velocity and force-length relationships are quite static or quasi-static. We maintain them under these highly controlled conditions. In fact, we get rid of
Jenna Monroy: the contributions of viscoelastic elements when we measure those properties. But most muscles undergo lots of length changes. In fact, we often think of our locomotor muscles as undergoing stretch-shortening cycles, and we know that muscle force changes with length and activation, and like Carissa mentioned earlier, that we think of history-dependent properties, sort of how is force changing with
Jenna Monroy: Stretch versus shortening.
Jenna Monroy: And there's a large amount of data now that support the function of Titan as being a viscoelastic spring in sarcomeres. And so let me just point out Titan once again. So, as you guys pointed out, this is a picture of a sarcomere.
Jenna Monroy: And what we're seeing is actually half a sarcomere, so you can see the Z disk on the far left-hand side, and this red structure in the middle, that's actually the middle of the sarcomere, that's the M line, and the other Z-disc would be off the screen on the right. And the green structure represents our thick filament, and the blue structure represents our thin filament, and I want you to pay attention to this yellow structure, which is
Jenna Monroy: Titan.
Jenna Monroy: And so Titan interacts with the thin filament at the Z-disc, and it runs all the way through the myosin core to the M line, where it interacts with another Titan filament. And so, it essentially creates this lattice that holds the thick filament relative to the thin filament, so it's responsible for what we call sort of interfilament spacing.
Jenna Monroy: Which can actually affect how they interact with each other. I am particularly interested in this I-band region, because that's the viscoelastic spring. And while you guys don't have to remember all the names, there's, like, these three parts to it that I'm interested in. We're gonna call it an Ig domain, we have this little red element that's called the N2A, and then we have something called a PVK. And the things to keep in mind is that
Jenna Monroy: The IG is kind of a spring, and the PVK is a spring, and that unique N2A, it's like this unique sequence, this unique structure.
Jenna Monroy: Alright.
Jenna Monroy: So, as you guys pointed out earlier.
Jenna Monroy: there's lots of evidence to suggest that Titan contributes to passive muscle stiffness. That is, when a muscle's passive, there's no calcium in the cell, you can stretch it out, and you do get some resistance, and you see this exponential relationship between the length
Jenna Monroy: and the force output. And you could do this with an individual Titan molecule, and it matches what you see in the muscle. So that's what we're seeing in this graph here. And we can attribute the different parts of Titan to our passive curve. This low force straightening, where you have, this low increase in force with a change in sarcomere, is associated with the stretch of this
Jenna Monroy: tandem IG. So this is kind of a spring, but it's kind of a compliant spring. But then, as you continue to stretch a sarcomere out, you would actually see that the force increases exponentially, and that is associated with this PVK domain. And I'm particularly interested in that PVK region, and
Jenna Monroy: The other thing that's interesting about Titan is that more and more evidence suggests that Titan
Jenna Monroy: contributes to active force. And…
Jenna Monroy: And so it's this tunable spring. It changes its stiffness when calcium floods the cell. So imagine that you're…
Jenna Monroy: your cell gets activated, you guys just talked about ECC, we see a release of calcium into the cell, and not only does it activate and expose our actin binding sites, but it actually facilitates the binding of this N2A region to the actin filament. And what it does is that it eliminates
Jenna Monroy: these tandem IGs, and it engages only that PVK domain. So, what we're doing is we're engaging that PVK domain at a shorter length.
Jenna Monroy: And that allows us to have this
Jenna Monroy: stiffer Titan stiffness when a muscle is activated, and now you can see that activate… this activated Titan could explain, sort of, how the stretch of this spring could potentially provide extra force in stretched muscles, and perhaps even empower amplification, like what we saw in our toad muscles. So, you got a spring in there you could store.
Jenna Monroy: elastic energy, you could release that energy when you do things like open your mouth really fast and project your tongue.
Jenna Monroy: Okay, the other thing that I'm interested in, so let's say Titan's contributing to passive force, it's contributing to active force.
Jenna Monroy: Titan varies across different muscles and species. We know now that it is at least… so, I'm going to talk about vertebrates specifically right now, but there's some cool questions in vertebrates. But in vertebrates, there's one single Titan gene.
Jenna Monroy: And that Titan gene can have various different exons be spliced out. So through that alternative splicing, you can have muscles that express long titan isoforms, and when you have a long isoform.
Jenna Monroy: you can… you're actually passively compliant, because you're much long… a longer spring. But you can have other tight nisoforms that are shorter.
Jenna Monroy: And then they are stiffer. And so what you're seeing here are… is the passive force of our soleus muscle in the leg. It has a really long, tight nisoform. It has all…
Jenna Monroy: all those exons in there, and so it has low passive force. But when you cut them all out like that in the psoas, or a lot of them out, now you have higher passive stiffness.
Jenna Monroy: So we can see that we can tune just the tight and stiffness in a muscle, depending on what these different muscles are doing.
Jenna Monroy: And…
Jenna Monroy: I can tell you that the PVK region in particular is where all that splicing is taking place. And I don't have a lot of time to explain all of this, but the point is, is that this, diagram below can show you which exons are being expressed in each of the different muscles. And I did a project with a student, in,
Jenna Monroy: In 2019, and what we did is we took
Jenna Monroy: the DNA and the sequence of the Titan gene from lots of different mammals, and I know you can't really see this slide, but I want you to see is just the variability. And so what we're looking at is a phylogeny of mammals from, you know, you've got your platypus and your marsupials at the top, and then various different placental mammals, and what you're seeing on the right is all these little pink and green stripes. That is the
Jenna Monroy: exon arrangement of your PVK region. And what I want you to just take note of is just, they're not the same. The number of exons, and even sort of the color, the pink and the green, kind of indicates how much P's, E's, V's, and K's are in there. So we can think about, sort of, the composition of the PVK, as well as the length of the PVK, and how those things might differ across
Jenna Monroy: different organisms. I can zoom in just on one piece so you can see a little better. So this includes our platypus at the top, down to our apes at the bottom. Again.
Jenna Monroy: what I want you to notice is that the number changes, how the color changes, and how similar it varies across the different organisms.
Jenna Monroy: Well, those, exons that are close to the N-terminus, we're calling that PVKN, are more similar, and so you can see just down… if you look down that, region, you can see that they're relatively the same. But then you look at the PVKC, the other side of the,
Jenna Monroy: of the Titan, and you can see it's highly variable. And so, there's lots of different variation in our PVKC region. Now, this is just the gene itself. Keep in mind, it still can undergo a lot of alternative splicing in one muscle compared to another muscle.
Jenna Monroy: All it tells us is how much variability you might see just across the organisms. So I am particularly interested in how Titan isoform expression can impact
Jenna Monroy: You know, various different, Performance, animal performance and muscle function.
Jenna Monroy: So, you know, one example that's really great in the literature is this paper by Manny Azizi, which maybe some of you are working with him this summer, where this was a 2014 paper where he looked at the function of the plantaris muscle in the leg and the inconus muscle in the forelimb. And the plantaris muscle
Jenna Monroy: It's responsible for powering the… powering the hop and the… and the toad.
Jenna Monroy: It's a… it shortens during, contraction, it produces mechanical energy, it produces power so you can jump.
Jenna Monroy: But the anconius, it undergoes active lengthening. It breaks as the animal lands on the ground. So the plantaris acts as a motor, whereas our anconius acts as a brake. So we see two muscles in the same organism that have very different functions, and one lengthens during, contraction, while the other one shortens.
Jenna Monroy: We also know the difference in their passive force, so they showed that the plantaris muscle is quite compliant.
Jenna Monroy: And compared to the Anconius, which is really stiff.
Jenna Monroy: And so, this begs all kinds of questions about Titan, where…
Jenna Monroy: Just based on the passive properties, we might guess, we might say, does the plantaris muscle
Jenna Monroy: express a longer, more compliant titan isoform compared to the Anconius? And then we could even ask, is that in the PVK region? Is it in that IG domain? We can also ask, how does active stiffness compare in these two organisms? And so this is… this has to do with that N2A region and the location of that N2A. Are we actually seeing the same
Jenna Monroy: same increase in stiffness with activation? Are we seeing something different between these muscles that differ in their… differ in their function?
Jenna Monroy: So, my goal here is to get you guys thinking about whatever project that you're working on as how Titan might be playing a role, and whether or not its properties and what isoform you might be expressing, is tuned to the behavior that you're interested in.
Jenna Monroy: Okay, so I know that we've kind of gone long here today, but hopefully what you're seeing is that we're kind of missing
Jenna Monroy: These measurements of muscle and tightened viscoelasticity from what we've traditionally learned in our muscle… in our physiology classes.
Jenna Monroy: Right? And so we need to start thinking about variation across muscles in the same way that you guys discussed today, but also when we think about Titan isoforms, and that these variation in Titan isoform could be matched to the behavioral demands of an organism.
Jenna Monroy: Okay, so I'm gonna unshare again.
Jenna Monroy: Right? Because we only have a few minutes. And so, maybe I'll open this up to discussion. Ideally, we were going to have you guys go into breakout rooms and… and come up with your own questions about Titan and muscle, and… but maybe I'm just opening it up for discussion to you guys. What,
Jenna Monroy: What questions do you have about this?
Adwait Mane: I have a question about what you presented regarding the Titan ISO forms.
Adwait Mane: Could you…
Adwait Mane: Maybe if you could share your slide, that would help, but I can just ask. What is the PEVK ratio? You had that, like.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah, yeah, yeah, the PDVK ratio. So, okay, so…
Jenna Monroy: if you remember, the exons were colored sort of green to pink. It was some sort of scale, right? And when you were green, it meant that that particular exons was entirely made up of P's, E's, V's, and K's. These are actually the names of the amino acids.
Jenna Monroy: Right? That are in that particular… that are being expressed, and those amino acids can tell us something about the composition. So, there's lots of repetition in some of them, they're almost all Ps, E's, V's, and K's. Turns out the E is, glutamate, and glutamate can actually change the charge of your Titan… of that particular, part of Titan. And in changing the charge, it can…
Jenna Monroy: impact the way in which the PVK interacts with actin, and that could potentially influence its stiffness. So, I'm interested in how the composition, that is the P's, E's, V's, and K's, actually impact the property of that region of Titan. Does that help?
Adwait Mane: So, what is… what does a low PVK ratio mean?
Jenna Monroy: Honestly, I don't know, right? But it might be more that, some of these regions are more interactive with actin, and so they have lots of E's in there, and some of them have less of those E's in there, and so they're less interactive with actin. Does that make sense?
Adwait Mane: Yeah, so I guess it's just a ratio of the four different… components.
Jenna Monroy: Yes, and and there can be some other things in there, but we're sort of…
Jenna Monroy: We're learning in steps, is that here's… we're kind of thinking about the P's, E's, V's, and case.
Adwait Mane: Thank you.
Jenna Monroy: Yes. Other thoughts? Questions?
Andrew M Thornton: what's sort of the relative contribution of Titan versus, like, Matrix components versus, like, inherent
Andrew M Thornton: Properties of the contractile components that Impact stiffness of the muscle.
Jenna Monroy: No, this is a good question. So, I… you're probably not going to be super satisfied with this, is that, first of all, is that, you know, historically, we thought the tendon was all the elastic… elasticity, and what we then realized is that, no, actually, muscles can recoil, too. They can store and recover elastic energy. And from our research on the frogs, you know, it was almost entirely the muscle, because there wasn't
Jenna Monroy: much tendon associated with it. So, what I'm going to tell you is that it's probably dependent on the structure of the muscle, is that in some cases, you might see more of the muscle kind of contributing than the tendon, because you don't have much tendon. In other cases, like, you think of cursorial mammals running with really long tendons, the tendons might be doing most of the work, and maybe the muscles don't have as much contribution, viscoelastic
Jenna Monroy: properties that are contributing to the work of the muscle. And then… and then others, they have this equal contribution. So my suspicion is that, it depends.
Jenna Monroy: If that's, you know, which is not a very satisfying answer. But, what I…
Jenna Monroy: what I would encourage us to do when we start asking questions is really thinking about, how can I test the contribution of the whole muscle tendon unit, and then really think about what's the muscle doing? Is it also, you know, storing and recovering elastic energy? Is it dissipating energy? And what is the tendon doing? And we need to think about both structures.
Jenna Monroy: I hope that answers your question some.
Andrew M Thornton: Yeah, it does. I would just ask, how would we go about Determining those relative contributions.
Jenna Monroy: No, this is a good question, and honestly, where I was hoping that we would go, is that, how do we test these things?
Jenna Monroy: So, I think the first thing that we can do is, like, let's start with what we know how to do. We know how to do these isolated muscle experiments, right? And so, kind of going back to, I think it was your comment earlier, is that we need to start doing some of these, work loops, or sort of simulated sort of length changes, stretch shortening cycles, where we know we can actually
Jenna Monroy: change the length of the muscle and look at how force changes with length. So in my lab, we do stretch experiments where we can characterize, you know, what's the impact of a stretch on the muscle. So I need to think about,
Jenna Monroy: I'm gonna, you know, the titan isoform, and I need to think about the muscle property there. Then, you might be able to think about, okay, what are… what is tendon doing in my system? If you're a system that… if you're in a system that has a big, long tendon, then maybe you also have to measure those tendon properties. And in some labs, which some of you might be part of, you might actually be studying the, properties of the
Jenna Monroy: higher muscle tendon unit. Things to know is that
Jenna Monroy: We all can't do everything, right? But, we can start to ask those questions and say, okay, how can I do this systematically? Can I characterize the muscle? Can I characterize the tendon? Can I think about this as an entire unit?
Andrew M Thornton: Thank you.
Jenna Monroy: Yeah.
Jenna Monroy: Other… other thoughts, questions, comments as we… before we leave?
Hedyeh Teymouri: Sorry, it seems that, the… Actually…
Hedyeh Teymouri: vertebrates, just use single titan mockles, but we have…
Hedyeh Teymouri: two different and independent protein in invertebrates, that they are acting as titan, like in Drosophila, for example.
Hedyeh Teymouri: My question is that, so, does having to separate
Hedyeh Teymouri: Or independently tunable protein, give invertebrates, some mechanical advantages in force generation, in comparison with us, or vertebrates.
Jenna Monroy: This is an excellent question. I'm going to tell you that I don't work on… I don't work on invertebrates, but I… I agree with your, assessment. So.
Jenna Monroy: just so everybody knows what I'm just talking about, is that in invertebrates, like your insects, like the Drosophila, there's more than one gene that expresses a titan-like molecule, and in that, you could have different isoforms of that. So, you can imagine that you just have more variability that you can play with. You can have, you know, it's not just one gene. Invertebrates, we only have one gene, and we can undergo
Jenna Monroy: All this,
Jenna Monroy: you know, alternative splicing. My suspicion is that there's just different ways to get variation. Invertebrates, we only have one gene, but we can undergo lots of different alternative splicing. In invertebrates, you seem to have more variation by expressing different genes.
Jenna Monroy: I think of… I think of myosins, right? We think of myosin isoforms as being associated with all our different fast twitch muscles, slow twitch muscles, but it has a family of genes as opposed to having one gene, so those are two different ways that you can get diversity.
Jenna Monroy: Alright, I know I'm going over time, so I apologize.
Jenna Monroy: I just want to make sure that everybody feels like they've gotten their questions answered at least a little bit.
Jenna Monroy: I appreciate you guys coming today, I know it was the first workshop, I had you guys doing a lot of things, I hope you learned something today. So, good luck this summer!
Victoria Wood: Thank you so much, Dr. Monroy, and thank you to all of you for attending. I put some links in the chat there, they're also in the Slack. Please make sure to upload your slides to the workshop folder, and then remember to complete that reflection slash sign-in form, so we can track attendance.
Victoria Wood: Thank you all!
Jenna Monroy: Bye, thank you!
Adwait Mane: Have a nice day.